大概俩个多月前发生个大新闻
Chris Anderson: So two months ago, something crazy happened
您能跟大家讲讲吗？因为这新闻刷了不少人的屏
Can you talk us through this, because this caught so many people's attention?
我先静静地让你们看视频
Gwynne Shotwell: I'll stay quiet for the beginning
一会我再说
and then I'll start talking
5,4,3,2,1
Voices: Five, four, three, two, one
重型猎鹰起飞
Woman: Liftoff. Go Falcon Heavy
这是太空叉多么重要的一刻啊
GS: So this was such an important moment for SpaceX
先是猎鹰9号，现在又有了重型猎鹰
With the Falcon 9 and now the Falcon Heavy
这样我们就能发射
we can launch into orbit
任何我们之前和现在想发射的载荷入轨
any payload that has previously been conceived or is conceived right now
我们计划今年晚些还有几发重猎
We've got a couple of launches of Falcon Heavy later this year
所以这首射一定得成功
so this had to go right
这是我们第一次发射重型猎鹰
It was the first time we flew it
当然还有最酷炫的那一幕
and the star of the show, of course
两个助推器同时着陆
brother and sister side boosters landing
我简直一颗赛艇
I was excited
感谢我的团队
Thanking my team
另外，当时在现场还有上千人
By the way, there's maybe a thousand people
站在我一圈附近
standing around me right there
还有这位Starman
And Starman
当然啦他存在感没有那么高
Starman did not steal the show, though --
俩助推才是主角
the boosters did
咱总该射点什么吧……那咱射辆特斯拉吧~
CA: There had to be some payload -- why not put a Tesla into space?
对吧，这主意厉害吧
GS: Exactly. It was perfect
格温，咱回想一下
CA: Gwynne, let's wind the clock back
你是怎么当上一位工程师，最后当上太空叉总裁的？
I mean, how did you end up an engineer and President of SpaceX?
你是那种很NERD的人吗？
Were you supernerdy as a girl?
我还真不觉得
GS: I don't think I was nerdy
但我的确做的事情和其它女孩不太一样
but I was definitely doing the things that the girls weren't doing
我妈妈是位艺术家，三年级的时候我问她
I asked my mom, who was an artist, when I was in third grade
车是怎么运转的
how a car worked
她肯定不懂啊，就给我一本书，我就读完了
so she had no idea so she gave me a book, and I read it
而且的确，我拿到机械工程学位以后第一份工作
and sure enough, my first job out of my mechanical engineering degree
就是在克莱斯勒造汽车
was with Chrysler Motors in the automotive industry
但我成为工程师这件事和那本书关系不大
But I actually got into engineering not because of that book
而是我妈妈带我去过美国女性工程师协会的一场活动
but because my mom took me to a Society of Women Engineers event
我深深爱上了活动演讲中提到的“机械工程”
and I fell in love with the mechanical engineer that spoke
那位演讲者做的工作是那么厉害
She was doing really critical work
我也超爱她当时的制服
and I loved her suit
我当时才15岁，想法很天真是吧
And that's what a 15-year-old girl connects with
之前我还挺不好意思讲这事的
And I used to shy away from telling that story
但这真的是我成为工程师的原因
but if that's what caused me to be an engineer --
现在我感觉应该讲出来了
hey, I think we should talk about that
十六年前，你成为太空叉第七位员工
CA: Sixteen years ago, you became employee number seven at SpaceX
之后几年
and then over the next years
太空叉争取到了和NASA的数十亿美元的合同
you somehow built a multi-billion-dollar relationship with NASA
尽管之前三发猎鹰一号全炸了
despite the fact that SpaceX's first three launches blew up
我想问的是，你们是怎么做到的
I mean, how on earth did you do that?
实际上啊，卖火箭就是在卖人脉
GS: So actually, selling rockets is all about relationships
和客户们建立各种关系
and making a connection with these customers
你要是没有火箭能卖
When you don't have a rocket to sell
这时重要的就是你得学会卖你的团队
what's really important is selling your team
推销你的CEO的商业头脑
selling the business savvy of your CEO --
如今这并不难
that's not really hard to sell these days --
而基本上你要保证他们的任何技术问题
and basically, making sure that any technical issue that they have
或者任何顾虑，你都能马上处理
or any concern, you can address right away
所以我认为作为一名工程师对此是很有帮助的
So I think it was helpful for me to be an engineer
这对我帮马一龙搞火箭的销售很有帮助
I think it was helpful to my role of running sales for Elon
那么目前贵司的工作重心
CA: And currently, a big focus of the company
我猜是和波音比赛
is, I guess, kind of a race with Boeing
谁先能帮助NASA
to be the first to provide the service to NASA
送人进太空？
of actually putting humans into orbit
这当中安全肯定是第一位的
Safety considerations obviously come to the fore, here
每每想到这些你能睡好吗？
How are you sleeping?
我睡觉没毛病，沾枕头就着，这是我最大的优点
GS: I actually sleep really well. I'm a good sleeper, that's my best thing
至于要坐我们火箭的人能不能睡着
But I think the days leading up to our flying crew
那就不好说了
will probably be a little sleepless
但讲真，基本上，安全与否取决于
But really, fundamentally, safety comes in the design
你将来要载人的系统的设计
of the system that you're going to fly people on
而这我们已经研究很多年了
and so we've been working for years
实际上在这方面技术上快有十年了
actually, almost a decade, on this technology
我们用龙飞船运货
We're taking the Dragon cargo spaceship
然后我们升级龙飞船，使其能载人
and we're upgrading it to be able to carry crew
像我说的，我们已经研发它的安全系统
And as I said, we've been engineering in these safety systems
很长一段时间了
for quite some time
所以是不是有个系统能帮助乘员快速逃生？
CA: So isn't it that there's one system that actually allows instant escape
如果发生故障的话
if there's a problem
没错，这个叫发射逃逸系统
GS: That's right. It's called the launch escape system
我们好像有视频，一起看看吧
CA: I think we have that. Let's show that
这是我们2015年做的测试视频
GS: We've got a video of a test that we ran in 2015
这天发射台天气挺差的
So this simulated having a really bad day on the pad
基本上你要让返回舱脱离危险
Basically, you want the capsule to get out of Dodge
你要让它离火箭越远越好
You want it to get away from the rocket
因为你下面的部分出问题了
that had a bad day right below it
视频里我们就假设下面发射台有麻烦了
This is if there was an issue on the pad
今年晚些时候我们还会做另一个演示
We also will be doing another demonstration later this year
演示在火箭飞行中出问题的解决办法
on if we have an issue with the rocket during flight
所以返回舱一圈的小火箭最终也是有隐藏功能的对吧
CA: And those rockets have another potential function as well, eventually
没错，所以龙飞船的发射逃逸系统很特别
GS: Yeah, so the launch escape system for Dragon is pretty unique
它是和返回舱整合在一起的
It's an integrated launch escape system
它基本就是一组推进器
It's basically a pusher
燃料系统和推进系统是整合在返回舱上的
so the propellant system and the thrusters are integrated into the capsule
如果龙飞船发现火箭有问题，逃逸系统就能带返回舱飞离火箭
and so if it detects a rocket problem, it pushes the capsule away
逃逸系统之前有点像个拖拉机（逃逸塔）
Capsule safety systems in the past have been like tractor pullers
而我们没这样做的原因
and the reason we didn't want to do that
是上面的逃逸塔在返回地球前必须分离
is that puller needs to come off before you can safely reenter that capsule
这样设计的时候就得评估这东西失效的概率有多大
so we wanted to eliminate, in design, that possibility of failure
太空叉现在已经能复用火箭了
CA: I mean, SpaceX has made the regular reusability of rockets
甚至复用火箭成了常态
seem almost routine
这说明你们已经有所成就了
which means you've done something
这个成就是比如其他国家级的太空项目
that no national space program, for example
从未做到过的
has been able to achieve
那你们是怎么做到的？
How was that possible?
我觉得有几点原因——
GS: I think there's a couple of things --
好吧其实是有几百万种原因——
there's a million things, actually --
成就了太空叉今日的成功
that have allowed SpaceX to be successful
首先我们是站在无数巨人的肩膀上的对吧？
The first is that we're kind of standing on the shoulders of giants. Right?
我们能够看到火箭工业最新的发展如何
We got to look at the rocket industry and the developments to date
我们能选出最好的点子
and we got to pick the best ideas
并充分发挥它们
leverage them
我们的火箭上也没啥非用不可的技术
We also didn't have technology that we had to include in our vehicle systems
所以不需要某些特别老的元件
So we didn't have to design around legacy components
不用费劲找特别可靠的或者非常贵的
that maybe weren't the most reliable or were particularly expensive
所以我们的确做到了让物理学来主导我们的系统设计
so we really were able to let physics drive the design of these systems
可是，还有很多项目也是从零开始的
CA: I mean, there are other programs started from scratch
你刚刚最后说你们让物理学主导设计
That last phrase you said there, you let physics drive the design
能具体说说例子吗？
what's an example of that?
实际这有上百个例子
GS: There's hundreds of examples, actually, of that
但基本上我们着手火箭设计的时候
but basically, we got to construct the vehicle design
真的是从一张白纸开始的
from, really, a clean sheet of paper
我们要亲自做每一个决定
and we got to make decisions that we wanted to make
比如燃料罐的设计，常见的半球形设计
The tank architecture -- it's a common dome design
简单来说就是俩啤酒罐摞一起
Basically it's like two beer cans stacked together
一个装液氧
one full of liquid oxygen
一个装火箭煤油
one full of RP
这样基本上能节省很多重量
and that basically saved weight
这能让我们基本上在同样设计下带更多载荷
It allowed us to basically take more payload for the same design
另外一个我们正在服役的火箭上一个特点就是
One of the other elements of the vehicle that we're flying right now
我们使用的是高密度的液氧和火箭煤油
is we do use densified liquid oxygen and densified RP
它们是超低温的
so it's ultracold
这能让你的火箭能装更多的燃料
and it allows you to pack more propellent into the vehicle
其他领域也有应用
It is done elsewhere
把非死不可的卫星炸了的程度？→_→
但可能没到我们的程度
probably not to the degree that we do it
但这让火箭运力有了很多上升空间
but it adds a lot of margin to the vehicle
这些空间可以用来提升火箭可靠性
which obviously adds reliability
格温，你十年前就是太空叉的总裁了，我想
CA: Gwynne, you became President of SpaceX 10 years ago, I think
和马一龙一起干活是啥感觉？
What's it been like to work so closely with Elon Musk?
呃……我很爱和马一龙一起工作
GS: So I love working for Elon
我和他共事实际上已经有16年了
I've been doing it for 16 years this year, actually
我不会蠢到做自己不喜欢的事情做16年
I don't think I'm dumb enough to do something for 16 years that I don't like doing
他挺有意思的
He's funny
基本上他啥都不用说
and fundamentally without him saying anything
你就能有把事情做到最好的动力
he drives you to do your best work
他啥话都不用说
He doesn't have to say a word
你单纯地想把工作做好
You just want to do great work
你可能最适合回答下面的问题了
CA: You might be the person best placed to answer this question
这问题让我很疑惑
which has puzzled me
能不能解释一个时间单位
which is to shed light on this strange unit of time
这段说的是马一龙总是画大饼 各种承诺的时间都超前得离谱
叫“马一龙时间”
called "Elon time."
我举个栗子，你也知道我去年问过马一龙
For example, last year, I asked Elon, you know
特斯拉啥时候能全美国自动驾驶
when Tesla would auto-drive across America
他说去年12月之前
and he said by last December
这我当然相信，前提是使用“马一龙时间”作为单位
which is definitely true, if you take Elon time into account
所以实际时间和“马一龙时间”之间换算比例是多少？
So what's the conversion ratio between Elon time and real time?
呃……你专门来问我这问题
GS: You put me in a unique position, Chris
我还真是荣幸
Thanks for that
大家也都知道马一龙总是把目标完成的时间吹的特别靠前
There's no question that Elon is very aggressive on his timelines
但讲道理正所谓截止日期才是第一生产力啊
but frankly, that drives us to do things better and faster
我觉得就算是全世界所有人的时间和所有人的钱
I think all the time and all the money in the world
也换不来最好的解决方案
does not yield the best solution
所以给团队施加适当压力来促进效率是很重要的
and so putting that pressure on the team to move quickly is really important
听上去你在这里有点像个和事老
CA: It feels like you play kind of a key intermediary role here
马一龙会定一些，有影响力的、疯狂的目标
I mean, he sets these crazy goals that have their impact
但另一个角度来说，这可能压垮一个团队
but, in other circumstances, might blow up a team
或者这个目标根本不可能
or set impossible expectations
然后你好像一直在旁边间接的说“好的老马”一样
It feels like you've found a way of saying, "Yes, Elon,"
然后想办法实现他的要求
and then making it happen in a way that is acceptable
这样既满足了他，也满足了公司和员工
both to him and to your company, to your employees
其实我认识到了非常重要的两点
GS: There is two really important realizations for that
第一个，当马一龙说什么事的时候，你得停下来
First of all, when Elon says something, you have to pause
你肯定不会马上说“拉倒吧”
and not immediately blurt out, "Well, that's impossible,"
或者马上回复说“我们办不到，我不知道咋整”
or, "There's no way we're going to do that. I don't know how."
相反你会静下来想想
So you zip it, and you think about it
然后你总能找到解决办法
and you find ways to get that done
第二点是
And the other thing I realized
就是我很难彻底完成自己想达成的成就
and it made my job satisfaction substantially harder
我感觉我的工作就是收到一堆想法
So I always felt like my job was to take these ideas
把它们变成公司的目标，想办法完成这些目标
and kind of turn them into company goals, make them achievable
就像在推着公司上一个斜坡
and kind of roll the company over from this steep slope, get it comfortable
每次我感觉快到了
And I noticed every time I felt like we were there
马上就快到顶了
we were rolling over, people were getting comfortable
这段比喻翻译过来挺蠢的 你们大概理解下就行
大致就是每当你这个活快干完的时候
老马那边就又开始作了 于是给你新任务做
马一龙就突然发难
Elon would throw something out there
突然间，大家又要重新开始
and all of a sudden, we're not comfortable
然后从头开始推公司上斜坡
and we're climbing that steep slope again
但后来我感觉，这其实就是他的工作
But then once I realized that that's his job
而我的工作是让公司一点点向上爬
and my job is to get the company close to comfortable
而他则指引我们该往哪爬
so he can push again and put us back on that slope
于是我就开始超级喜欢我的工作
then I started liking my job a lot more
而不是天天抱怨
instead of always being frustrated
所以我估摸下换算的比例
CA: So if I estimated that the conversation ratio
“马一龙时间”和你的时间差不多是两倍关系？
for Elon time to your time is about 2x
我估计的如何？
am I a long way out there?
我觉得凑合吧，这可是你说的啊，不是我说的
GS: That's not terrible, and you said it, I didn't
呃，咱们回到现在
CA: You know, looking ahead
有个大项目
one huge initiative
大家都说太空叉又在搞一个大新闻
SpaceX is believed to be, rumored to be working on
发射上千个近地卫星构成一个大型网络
is a massive network of literally thousands of low earth orbit satellites
从而提供高带宽、低成本的网络连接
to provide high-bandwidth, low-cost internet connection
覆盖地球每个角落
to every square foot of planet earth
对此你有什么要说的吗？
Is there anything you can tell us about this?
我们其实并不常说这个计划
GS: We actually don't chat very much about this particular project
不是我们故意装神秘
not because we're hiding anything
但这计划可能不算人类最难
but this is probably one of the most challenging
也起码是我们遇到过最有挑战的计划
if not the most challenging project we've undertaken
还没谁做到过
No one has been successful
部署一个超大卫星星座来做互联网广播
deploying a huge constellation for internet broadband
或者单纯的卫星网络
or basically for satellite internet
我不认为这里物理学是难题
and I don't think physics is the difficulty here
找到正确的技术解决方案并不难
I think we can come up with the right technology solution
难点是从中赚钱
but we need to make a business out of it
这个系统要花费公司至少一百亿来部署
and it'll cost the company about 10 billion dollars or more to deploy this system
所以我们目前还在有条不紊的干
And so we're marching steadily along
但离成功还远着呢
but we're certainly not claiming victory yet
我想问这件事的影响，显然，如果你说这发生的话
CA: I mean, the impact of that, obviously, if that happened to the world
全球都能覆盖互联网，这太激进了吧
of connectivity everywhere, would be pretty radical
或许大部分是好事
and perhaps mainly for good --
我是说，突然间大家都能连上廉价的网络了
I mean, it changes a lot if suddenly everyone can connect cheaply
嗯，毫无疑问这绝对会改变世界
GS: Yeah, there's no question it'll change the world
这当中有什么顾虑吗？
CA: How much of a worry is it
该计划的具体难点在什么地方？
and how much of a drag on the planning is it
比如太空垃圾的顾虑？
are concerns just about space junk?
民众对此挺担忧的
People worry a lot about this
该系统会大大增加在轨卫星数量
This would a huge increase in the total number of satellites in orbit
这需要担忧吗？
Is that a concern?
呃太空垃圾的确要考虑，这毫无疑问
GS: So space debris is a concern, there's no question --
不是说发生概率大
not because it's so likely to happen
而是说一旦发生，后果极其严重
but the consequences of it happening are pretty devastating
后果基本上相当于在轨道撒一大堆东西
You could basically spew a bunch of particles in orbit
可能让这条轨道荒废几十年或者更久
that could take out that orbit from being useful for decades or longer
所以实际上
So as a matter of fact
我们每次发射任务也都有要求，让二级受控再入
we are required to bring down our second stage after every mission
而不是让二级变成一个环绕地球的太空垃圾
so it doesn't end up being a rocket carcass orbiting earth
这方面管理的确要做到位
So you really need to be a good steward of that
那么尽管重猎火箭发射成功了
CA: So despite the remarkable success there of that Falcon Heavy rocket
但你们现在并没有把太大精力放在上面
you're actually not focusing on that as your future development plan
你们正在加班加点地造一个更大的火箭
You're doubling down to a much bigger rocket
名叫BFR
called the BFR
全称是……
which stands for ..
这里笑点在BFR之前外号叫Big Fucking Rocket
大猎鹰火箭
GS: It's the Big Falcon Rocket
大猎鹰火箭，对对对
CA: The Big Falcon Rocket, that's right
你们做这个的商业逻辑在于何处？
What's the business logic of doing this
你们已经有了那么多了不起的技术了
when you invested all that in that incredible technology
为啥还要单纯地造更大的东西呢？
and now you're just going to something much bigger. Why?
实际上这算是我们的教训吧
GS: Actually, we've learned some lessons
开发火箭发射系统这么久以来
over the duration where we've been developing these launch systems
我们不想在说服客户之前把新产品的想法摆上来
What we want to do is not introduce a new product before we've been able
to convince the customers that this is the product that they should move to
所以我们现在就造BFR
so we're working on the Big Falcon Rocket now
但我们的猎鹰九号和重猎还是正常继续飞
but we're going to continue flying Falcon 9s and Falcon Heavies
直到未来BFR真正推广
until there is absolute widespread acceptance of BFR
但我们现在已经在做了
But we are working on it right now
我们不可能一下子让猎鹰九号和重猎退役
we're just not going to cancel Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy
然后马上换上BFR
and just put in place BFR
可是贵司想用BFR送人类去火星？
CA: The logic is that BFR is what you need to take humanity to Mars?
没错
GS: That's correct
但你们发现了其中的商业契机？
CA: But somehow, you've also found other business ideas for this
是的，BFR能送我们现在送不了的卫星入轨
GS: Yes. BFR can take the satellites that we're currently taking to orbit
很多种轨道
to many orbits
它甚至能送船新类型的卫星入轨
It allows for even a new class of satellites to be delivered to orbit
主要原因是BFR整流罩直径达八米
Basically, the width, the diameter of the fairing is eight meters
你可以想想一些大型的望远镜
so you can think about what giant telescopes
你可以把它放进整流罩，就是BFR的货仓
you can put in that fairing, in that cargo bay
用它去看很多厉害的东西
and see really incredible things
去发现宇宙中各种厉害的事情
and discover incredible things in space
当然我们还挖掘出BFR的一些冗余能力
But then there are some residual capabilities that we have out of BFR as well
冗余能力？
CA: A residual capability?
是的，冗余能力
GS: It's a residual capability
你是说这个吗？跟我们讲讲这特喵是啥？
CA: Is that what you call this? Talk about what the heck this is
呃等下——
Oh wait a sec --
这是重型猎鹰火箭
GS: That's Falcon Heavy
这图其实也有些值得说的
That's worth pointing out, by the way
看这火箭多漂亮呀
What a beautiful rocket
它的厂房能装下整个自由女神像
and that hangar could just fit the Statue of Liberty in it
所以你可以想象这重型猎鹰有多大
so you get a sense of size of that Falcon Heavy Rocket
另外图里这27台发动机
CA: And the fact that there are 27 engines there
也是你们的设计原则吗？
That's part of the design principle
你们不会简单地造更大的火箭
that you, rather than just inventing ever bigger rockets
而是把小火箭组合起来
you team them up
没错，这就是我刚说的冗余能力
GS: It's exactly this residual capability
我们当年开发了猎鹰一号的梅林发动机
We developed the Merlin engine for the Falcon 1 launch vehicle
我们完全可以不用它
We could have tossed that engine
然后为猎鹰九号开发新发动机
and built an entirely new engine for the Falcon 9
虽然那样肯定就不叫“猎鹰九号”了
It would have been called something different
因为猎鹰九号下面有九台梅林发动机
because Falcon 9 is nine Merlin engines
但与其花上百万研发新发动机
but instead of spending a billion dollars on a brand new engine
我们不如在猎鹰九号下面放九台发动机并联
we put nine of them together on the back end of Falcon 9
冗余能力是什么呢？我们还可以把三发猎鹰九号粘起来
Residual capability: glue three Falcon 9s together
于是就得到了现役最强运力的火箭
and you have the largest operational rocket flying
虽然还是很贵
And so it was expensive to do
但也比从零开始高效得多
but it was a much more efficient path than starting from scratch
那BFR和这相比有多大呢？
CA: And the BFR is the equivalent of how much bigger than that
按推力来比较的话？
in terms of its power?
BFR大概是……我相信是图里的2.5倍吧
GS: BFR is about, I believe, two and half times the size of this
好吧，所以那样你们就能……
CA: Right, and so that allows you --
不行我实在还是不敢相信我们接下来要放的视频
I mean, I still don't really believe this video that we're about to play here
这特喵是啥？？？
What on earth is this?
这里目前是在地球
GS: So it currently is on earth
这里演示的就是地球上的旅行方式
but this is basically space travel for earthlings
我已经等不及这个冗余能力了
I can't wait for this residual capability
我们要做的，基本上就是让BFR变成像民航客机一样
Basically, what we're going to do is we're going to fly BFR like an aircraft
做地球上的点对点旅行
and do point-to-point travel on earth
你可以从纽约或者温哥华起飞
so you can take off from New York City or Vancouver
跨越半个地球
and fly halfway across the globe
飞行时间大概在半小时到四十分钟
You'll be on the BFR for roughly half an hour or 40 minutes
最长的部分——喔谢谢，的确看上去很厉害
and the longest part -- yeah, it's so awesome
整个旅途最长的部分是坐船往返的时间
The longest part of that flight is actually the boat out and back
我是说，格温，咱能别吹了吗？吹牛起码该打个草稿吧？
CA: I mean. Gwynne, come on, this is awesome, but it's crazy, right?
你这肯定全是骗人的吧
This is never going to actually happen
不，这肯定能发生
GS: Oh no, it's definitely going to happen
这绝对绝对会变成现实
This is definitely going to happen
怎么说？
CA: How?
首先，国家就要接受一个像洲际导弹一样的东西飞过去
So first of all, countries are going to accept this incoming missile --
Chris，你知道我们尝试说服联邦的一块地
GS: Chris, so can you imagine us trying to convince a federal range
一个空军基地让我们的火箭飞过去吗？
Air Force bases to take the incomers?
因为我们现在就在这样做啊
Because we're doing it now, regularly, right?
我们早就能让一级火箭飞回来
We're bringing the first stages back
然后让它降落在美利坚的领土——一个空军基地上
and we're landing them on federal property on an Air Force base
所以我们才会搞这个……比如说
So I think doing it, I don't know
降落在城市外十公里，或许更近，五公里
10 kilometers out from a city, maybe it's only five kilometers out from a city
那有多少人可能承担得起这趟太空旅行的票价呢
CA: So how many passengers can possibly afford the fortune of flying by space?
第一代BFR大概能载一百人吧
GS: So the first BFR is going to have roughly a hundred passengers
咱们现在简单算一笔账
And let's talk a little bit about the business
大家都感觉火箭是很贵的
Everyone thinks rockets are really expensive
他们这样想没错
and to a large degree they are
我们这怎么和航司比价格呢？
and how could we possibly compete with airline tickets here?
但你这样想，如果我每段旅程
But if you think about it, if I can do this trip
都在半小时到一小时内
in half an hour to an hour
那我一天能飞十多次对吧
I can do dozens of these a day, right?
而远程客机这个距离一天只能飞一次
And yet, a long-haul aircraft can only make one of those flights a day
所以即使我们的火箭稍微贵一点
So even if my rocket was slightly more expensive
燃料也贵一点
and the fuel is a little bit more expensive
但我一天能跑十趟
I can run 10x at least what they're running in a day
这样我们实现盈利是完全有可能的
and really make the revenue that I need to out of that system
所以你真的认为这未来某天会成为现实？
CA: So you really believe this is going to be deployed at some point
大概要多久呢？
in our amazing future. When?
十年内，我保证
GS: Within a decade, for sure
这是“格温时间”还是“马一龙时间”？
CA: And this is Gwynne time or Elon time?
格温时间，马一龙说的话肯定更快
GS: That's Gwynne time. I'm sure Elon will want us to go faster
好吧真的惊了
CA: OK, that's certainly amazing
我个人就在投资这项计划，因为我经常满世界跑
GS: I'm personally invested in this one, because I travel a lot
但我讨厌舟车劳顿的感觉
and I do not love to travel
利雅得是沙特阿拉伯首都
所以我很期待早上从家出发去见利雅得的客户
and I would love to get to see my customers in Riyadh
然后谈完晚上回家吃饭
leave in the morning and be back in time to make dinner
所以我们会一起期待
CA: So we're going to test this out
在十年内，花经济舱的票价
So within 10 years, an economy price ticket
或者，比如纽约飞上海，每人几千块？
or, like, a couple thousand dollars per person to fly New York to Shanghai
嗯，我估计票价会介于经济舱和商务舱之间
GS: Yeah, I think it'll be between economy and business
但只要花一小时
but you do it in an hour
好吧这的确太厉害了
CA: Yeah, well, OK, that is definitely something
同时BFR还有其他用途仍在开发
And meanwhile, the other use of BFR is being developed
要去比上海远一点的地方
to go a little bit further than Shanghai
来讲讲吧
Talk about this
你们已经有一个非常详细的……构想？
You guys have actually developed quite a detailed, sort of, picture
关于人类如何去火星的
of how humans might fly to Mars
具体讲讲呢？
and what that would look like
好，这有段剪辑过的视频
GS: Yeah. So we've got a video, this is a cropped video
之前发布过，有些小改动
from others we've shown, and then there's a couple of new bits to it
但基本上就是从发射架上起飞
But basically, you're going to lift off from a pad
下面的助推和BFS——大猎鹰飞船
you've got a booster as well as the BFS, the Big Falcon Spaceship
它们一起起飞
It's going to take off
其实助推不会入轨
助推送飞船到一定速度后分离 然后掉头返回 飞船用自身燃料继续完成入轨
助推会送飞船入轨
The booster is going to drop the spaceship off in orbit
近地轨道
low earth orbit
然后飞回来，像太空叉现在做的一样
and then return just like we're returning boosters right now
听起来难以置信，但我们正在完善细节
So it sounds incredible, but we're working on the pieces
你也将会看到这些细节
and you can see us achieve these pieces
然后助推飞回来
So booster comes back
这里不同的是
The new thing here
助推直接落回出发的发射架上
is that we're going to actually land on the pad that we launched from
我们目前猎鹰九号是落在着陆场或者船上的
Currently, we land on a separate pad, or we land out on a boat
然后快速连接
Fast, quick connect
送一艘装满燃料的货船
You take a cargo ship full of fuel
或者就是个加油站
or a fuel depot
放在助推上面，送它入轨
put it on that booster, get that in orbit
对接，给飞船加油
do a docking maneuver, refuel the spaceship
然后去你的下一个目的地
and head on to your destination
这次，是火星
and this one is Mars
所以就是，一次送大概一百人去火星
CA: So, like, a hundred people go to Mars at one time
大概要多久？六个月？两个月？
taking, what, six months? Two months?
这取决于火箭到底多大
GS: It ends up depending on how big the rocket is
我想的这个是最初版本，我们将来还会造更大的BFR
I think this first version, and we'll continue to make even bigger BFRs
我估计三个月就能到
I think it's a three-month trip
现在的话需要六到八个月
Right now, the average is six to eight
但我们正在想办法更快
but we're going to try to do it faster
你认为太空叉多久能送人去火星？
CA: When do you believe SpaceX will land the first human on Mars?
这和我之前说的点对点的时间差不多
GS: It's a very similar time frame from the point-to-point
因为这两者功能相似
It's the same capability
所以还是十年之内……不是年代的那个十年
It will be within a decade -- not this decade
哇竟然是真实时间，哇，只需要十年
CA: In real time, again, within a decade
好吧，这真吓到我了
Well, that would also be amazing
所以……讲真……图个啥？
Why, though? Seriously, why?
我想问，贵司现在已经把这当成正经的目标来做了
I mean, you've got a company where this is the official stated mission
每个人都在做吗？
Has everyone actually bought into that mission
我的意思是，这世界上从来不缺人
given that, I mean, there's a lot of people around
你这也从来不缺脑子够用的人
who think, come on, you've got so much talent
也有那么多技术积累
so much technology capability
地球上还有那么多要做的事情
There are so many things on earth that need urgent attention
为啥你们非得研究怎么从地球去别的星球呢？
Why would you have this escape trip off to another planet?
啊很高兴你能问这个问题
GS: So I am glad you asked that
但我们应该想得更长远一点
but I think we need to expand our minds a little bit
地球上的确有很多事情可以做
There are plenty of things to do on earth
但也从来不缺公司去做那些事情
but there are lots of companies working on that
而我认为我们正在做的是我们能做到的最重要的事情
I think we're working on one of the most important things we possibly can
即寻找其他人类可生存、居住、繁衍的星球
and that's to find another place for humans to live and survive and thrive
如果地球出什么意外
If something happened on earth
人类总得找个地方吧
you need humans living somewhere else
这是在为全人类降低风险
It's the fundamental risk reduction for the human species
而且这和大家让地球更美好、保护地球是完全不矛盾的
And this does not subvert making our planet here better and doing a better job taking care of it
但我认为，总得留个退路
but I think you need multiple paths to survival
而我们正致力于此
and this is one of them
我们不说这些悲观的事情
And let's not talk about the downer piece
比如，你为了保证地球的物种不会死光而去火星
like, you go to Mars to make sure all earthlings don't die
这种想法、理由其实是很糟糕的
That's terrible, actually, that's a terrible reason to go do it
实际上，不停探索
Fundamentally, it's another place to explore
正是我们人类与其他物种的不同之处
and that's what makes humans different from animals
我们有好奇之心、探索之心
it's our sense of exploration and sense of wonderment
有对知识的渴望
and learning something new
我还要说的是
And then I also have to say
这只是我们前往其他太阳系的第一步
this is the first step in us moving to other solar systems
甚至其他星系
and potentially other galaxies
我觉得只在这方面我想的比马一龙还要远
and I think this is the only time I ever out-vision Elon
因为我真的想看看其他星系的文明
because I want to meet other people in other solar systems
火星已经挺好了，但还要好好打理
Mars is fine, but it is a fixer-upper planet
才能好好使其适宜人类居住
There's work to do there to make it habitable
我想找其他星系的“人”，或这“它”们自称什么
I want to find people, or whatever they call themselves, in another solar system
这真的太远大了
CA: That is a big vision
格温女士，谢谢您
Gwynne Shotwell, thank you
你做着地球上最流批的工作
You have one of the most amazing jobs on the planet
非常感谢
GS: Thank you very much. Thanks, Chris